Guide to the Rochella Thorpe oral history project files,1992-1995.
Thorpe, Rochella oral history project files,1992-1995.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Rochella Thorpe oral history project files, 1992-1995.
7607
Rochella Thorpe
.4 cubic ft.; 137 tape recordings, plus one box.
Audiotapes and transcripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Tape recordings and transcripts of interviews with lesbians, mostly African-American and white, who lived in Detroit in the post-World War II period, 1947-1975.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
As a doctoral student in the History Department of Binghamton University, Rochella (Roey) Thorpe researched lesbian life in Detroit, 1947-1975. She looked at the quite separate environments of African-American and white lesbians created in the Post War era. Within racial groups, lesbians mostly associated with women of similar economic backgrounds. Rather than finding one homogenous lesbian community, Thorpe found many different lesbian communities, and looked at the ways these communities and their survival strategies changed over time.
Her study is based in Detroit, a city that saw great urban growth and racial tension prior to and during World War II. Women's work in Detroit's wartime factories represented significant changes for both white and African-American women. After World War II, the fear of spreading communism in the automobile unions made Detroit the site of the 1951 House UnAmerican Activities Committee investigations. Detroit was a Midwest center for the civil rights, anti-war, and feminist movements of the 1960s and the emergence of the gay liberation movement in the 1970s. In 1970, Detroit women formed a chapter of the Daughters of Bilitis, and the radical newspaper THE DETROIT GAY LIBERATOR began publishing.
Thorpe's study includes substantial interviews with lesbians who lived in Detroit over this time period. Thorpe was the first openly lesbian candidate to be elected to the City of Ithaca (N.Y.) Common Council. The 5th Ward elected her as Alderwoman for a term from 1994 through 1997.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Tape recordings of interviews with fifty lesbians, mostly African-American and white, who lived in Detroit in the post-World War II period, 1947-1975. Transcripts are available for twenty-three interviews.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Thorpe, Rochella.
Subjects:
Lesbians--Michigan--Detroit--Social life and customs.; African American Lesbians--Michigan--Detroit--Social life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Interviews
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Collecting Program: Human Sexuality Collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Transcripts for tapes 7360a-7426a (Box 1, Folder 1-23)
- Copies of transcripts in box 1 (Box 2, Folder 1-23)
- Audiotapes
  All of the tapes in this collection have been digitized, for access please contact RMC staff.
  - Mable, 1992-06-24; tr7360a - tr7362a
  - Linda, 1992-08-28; tr7363a, tr7364a
  - Anita, 1992-06-29; tr7365a - tr7368a
  - Judy, 1992-06-25; tr7369a - tr7372a
  - Marie, 1992-06-30; tr7373a - tr7376a
  - B. Koz, 1992-08-22; tr7377a - tr7379a
  - Muriel, 1992-06-23; tr7380a - tr7382a
  - C.B. (Claire), 1992-02-07; tr7383a, tr7384a
  - Renee, 1992-06-24; tr7385a - tr7387a
  - Sher, 1992-08-15; tr7388a - tr7390a
    Tape tr7390a is blank.
  - Larry, 1992-08-01; tr7391a - tr7393a
  - Carol Kironac, 1992-06-08; tr7394a - tr7396a
  - Beth Brant, 1992-08-03; tr7397a - tr7400a
  - Jay, 1992-08-16; tr7401a - tr7402a
  - Sue, 1992-08-27; tr7403a - tr7404a
  - Gay Whiteside, Undated; tr7405a - tr7407a
  - Rebecca, 1992-08-05; tr7408a - tr7410a
  - Sharon, 1992-06-14; tr7411a - tr7414a
  - Martha, 1992-07-05; tr7415a - tr7417a
  - Pat Pardee, 1991-11-15; tr7418a
  - Melloniece, 1992-06-27; tr7419a - tr7420a
  - Elvira, 1992-06-25; tr7421a - tr7425a
  - Chuck Alexander, 1992-02-06; tr7426a
  - Ruth Ellis, 1992-01-16; tr7917a
  - Billie Hill, 1992-01-24; tr7918a - tr7920a
  - Beverly Dale, 1992-02-08; tr7921a
  - Judith Hill, 1992-02-06; tr7922a - tr7923a
  - Margaret Butler, 1992-02-05; tr7924a
  - Carol Hoke, Undated; tr7925a - tr7926a
    Tape tr7926a is blank.
  - Sonya Show: Donna and Suzie, 1982-01-12; tr7927a
  - Brandy, 1992-06-23; tr7928a - tr7931a
  - Toni, 1992-06-17; tr7932a - tr7934a
  - Billie Jo and Jessica, Undated; tr7935a - tr7936a
  - Thelma, Diane, JP, Undated; tr7937a - tr7943a
  - Party at JB's, Undated; tr7944a - tr7945a
    Note on case:"this tape is a conversation between [Roey], JB, Caerdwyn, Mari, and a woman who prefers to remain anonymous (trades woman)."
  - Veronica Crump, 1992-06-05; tr7946a - tr7949a
  - Karla Baldwin, 1992-06-03; tr7950a - tr7952a
  - Mary Ellen S., 1992-02-04; tr7953a
  - Marilyn, 1992-06-12; tr7954a - tr7958a
  - Margaret Lorick, Undated; tr7959a - tr7961a
  - Alice, 1992-08-26; tr7961a - tr7963a
  - Margaret and Alice, 1992-08-26; tr7963a - tr7965a
  - Evelyn (Lynne), 1992-06-16; tr7966a - tr7972a
  - Sarah, 1992-08-26; tr7973a - tr7975a
  - Sylvia, 1992-06-19; tr7976a
  - Ruth, 1992-08-21; tr7977a - tr7979a
  - JB and friends, 1992-08-10; tr7980a - tr7982a
  - Katherine, 1992-08-11; tr7983a - tr7986a
    Tape tr7986a is blank.